<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2111" status="Review">
<title>Which <tt>unexpected</tt>&#47;<tt>terminate</tt> handler is called from the exception handling runtime?</title>
<section><sref ref="[terminate]"/>,<sref ref="[unexpected]"/></section>
<submitter>Howard Hinnant</submitter>
<date>6 Dec 2011</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>

<p>
Prior to N3242, modified by N3189, we said this about <tt>unexpected()</tt>:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
<i>Effects</i>: Calls the <tt>unexpected_handler</tt> function in effect immediately after evaluating the throw-expression 
(D.13.1), if called by the implementation, or calls the current <tt>unexpected_handler</tt>, if called by the program.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
and this about <tt>terminate()</tt>:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
<i>Effects</i>: Calls the <tt>terminate_handler</tt> function in effect immediately after evaluating the throw-expression (18.8.3.1), 
if called by the implementation, or calls the current <tt>terminate_handler</tt> function, if called by the program.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
But now in both places we say:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
Calls the current <tt>unexpected_handler</tt> function.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
and:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
Calls the current <tt>terminate</tt> function.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
The difference is that in C++98&#47;03 if a destructor reset a handler during stack unwinding, that new handler was 
not called if the unwinding later led to <tt>unexpected()</tt> or <tt>terminate()</tt> being called.  But these new 
words say that this new handler <em>is</em> called. This is an ABI-breaking change in the way exceptions are handled.  
Was this change intentional?
<p/>
N3189 was mainly about introducing exception safety and getters for the handlers. I don't recall the issue of 
<em>which</em> handler gets called being part of the discussion.
<p/>
I propose that we revert to the C++98&#47;03 behavior in this regard, lest ABI's such as the Itanium ABI are invalidated.  
A mechanical way to do this is to revert bullets 9 and 12 of N3189.
</p>

<note>2011-12-09: Daniel comments</note>

<p>
There was no such semantic change intended. It was an unfortunate side effect when trying to better separate different
responsibilities in the previous wording.
<p/>
A related issue is <iref ref="2088"/>.
</p>

<note>2012-01-30: Howard comments</note>

<p>
The C++98&#47;03 wording is somewhat ambiguous:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
Calls the terminate_handler function in effect immediately after evaluating the throw-expression...
</p></blockquote>
<p>
There are potentially two throw-expressions being referred to here, and it is not clear if this sentence is referring to just the first or both:
</p>
<ol>
<li><tt>throw <i>assignment-expression</i>;</tt></li>
<li><tt>throw;</tt></li>
</ol>
<p>
There is ample evidence in current implementations that it is understood that <i>only</i> 
1. was meant. But clearly both 1 and 2 could have been meant. We need a clarification. Does an execution 
of a rethrow (throw;) update which handlers can potentially be called?
</p>
<ol>
<li value="2"><tt>throw;</tt> // update handlers to get_xxx()?</li>
</ol>
<p>
My opinion: Go with existing practice, and clarify what that practice is, if surveys find that everyone 
does the same thing. Gcc 4.2 and Apple do 1. only, and do not reset the handlers to the current handlers 
on throw;.
<p/>
If current practice is not unanimously one way or the other, I have no strong opinion. I have not found 
a motivating use case for the use of any particular handler. Most applications set the handlers once at 
the beginning of the program and then do not change them, and so will not be impacted by whatever decision 
is made here.
</p>

<note>2014-02-15 Issaquah: Move to Review</note>

<p>
STL: Original change in N3242 came from trying to make set/get exception handler thread safe.
The issue requests we revert to 98/03, which Howard notes was already ambiguous.
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: Issue author thinks we made this change in C++11 without taking into account Itanium ABI,
which cannot implement the new semantic (without breaking compatibility).
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: original change in N3242 was trying to solve the problem of which handler is called when
the handler is changing in another thread, but this turns out to be an issue in even the
single-threaded case.
</p>

<p>
Pablo: despite wanting to make it thread safe, you are still changing a global
</p>

<p>
STL and Marshall confirm that there is real implementation divergance on the question, so
we cannot pick just one behavior if we want to avoid breaking exisitng practice.
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: not sure who to talk to across all library vendors to fix, need more information
for progress (IBM and Sun)
</p>

<p>
STL: Howard did identify a problem with the wording as well: <tt>throw;</tt> is a throw expression,
but we typically want to re-activate the in-flight exception, not throw a new copy.
</p>

<p>
Pablo: wondering why all of this wording is here (N3189)? It looks like we were trying to handle another thread
changing handler between a <tt>throw</tt> and <tt>terminate</tt> in current thread.
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: Anything working with exception handling should have used only thread-local resources, but that ship has sailed.
We must account for the same exception object being re-thrown in multiple threads simultaneously, with no happens-before
relationships.
</p>

<p>
Room: Why on earth would we care about exactly which way the program dies when the terminate calls are racing?!
</p>

<p>
Pablo: Reasonable to set the handler once (in <tt>main</tt>) and never change it.
</p>

<p>
Pablo: If willing to put lots of work into this, you could say at point of a <tt>throw</tt> these handlers become
thread local but that is overkill.  We want destructors to be able to change these handlers (if only for backwards
compatibility).
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: the <i>&quot;do it right&quot;</i> is to do something per thread, but that is more work than vendors will want to do.
Want to say setting handler while running multiple threads is unspecified.
</p>

<p>
Pablo: possible all we need to do is say it is always the current handler
</p>

<p>
STL: That prevents an implementation or single threaded program from calling a new handler after a <tt>throw</tt>,
probably should say if <tt>terminate</tt> is called <i>by the implementation</i> (during EH), any handler that was
current can be called.  Leaves it up in the air as to when the handler is captured, supporting the diverging
existing practices.
</p>

<p>
Jeffrey: use <i>happens before</i> terminology to avoid introducing races
</p>

<p>
STL: Give this to concurrency?
</p>

<p>
Jeffrey: It is in clause 18, generally LWG and not SG1 territory.
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: Concerned about introducing <i>happens before</i> into fundamental exception handling since it would affect
single threaded performance as well.  Want to give to concurrency or LEWG/EWG, we are into language design here.
</p>

<p>
Jeffrey: suspect LEWG won't have a strong opinion.  I don't want it to be ours!!!
</p>

<p>
Pablo: Might be a case for core>
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: Would be happier if at least one core person were in the discussion.
</p>

<p>
STL: No sympathy for code that tries to guard the terminate handler.
</p>

<p>
Alisdair: We are back to set it once, globally.  Want to be clear that if <tt>set_terminate</tt> is called just once,
when EH is not active, and never changed again, then the user should get the handler from that specific call.
</p>

<p>
AlisdairM: "unspecified which handler is called if an exception is active when <tt>set_terminate</tt> is called."
This supports existing behaviors, and guarantees which handler is called in non-conentious situations.  Implicit
assumption that a funtion becomes a handler only after a successful call to <tt>set_handler</tt>, so we are not
leaving a door open to the implementation inventing entirely new handlers of its own.
</p>

<p>
<i>Consensus.</i>
</p>

<p>
Poll to confirm status as P1: new consensus is P3
</p>

<p>
<i>Action:</i> Alisdair provides new wording.  Drop from P1 to P3, and move to Review.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>
Amend <sref ref="[terminate]"/> as indicated:
</p>

<tt>[[noreturn]] void terminate() noexcept;</tt>
<blockquote><p>
<i>Remarks:</i> Called by the implementation when exception handling must be abandoned for any of several reasons (15.5.1)
<del>, in effect immediately after throwing the exception</del>. May also be called directly by the program.
</p></blockquote>

<blockquote><p>
<i>Effects:</i> <ins>Calls a <tt>terminate_handler</tt> function.  It is unpecified which <tt>terminate_handler</tt> function will
be called if an exception is active during a call to <tt>set_terminate</tt>.  Otherwise c</ins><del>C</del>alls the current
<tt>terminate_handler</tt> function. [<i>Note:</i> A default <tt>terminate_handler</tt> is always considered a callable handler in
this context. <i>- end note</i> ]
</p></blockquote>

<p>
Amend <sref ref="[unexpected]"/> as indicated:
</p>

<tt>[[noreturn]] void unexpected();</tt>
<blockquote><p>
Remarks: Called by the implementation when a function exits via an exception not allowed by its <i>exception-specification</i>
(15.5.2)<del>, in effect after evaluating the throw-expression (D.11.1)</del>. May also be called directly by the program.
</p></blockquote>

<blockquote><p>
<i>Effects:</i> <ins>Calls an <tt>unexpected_handler</tt> function.  It is unspecified which <tt>unexpected_handler</tt>
function will be called if an exception is active during a call to <tt>set_unexpected</tt>.  Otherwise
c</ins><del>C</del>alls the current <tt>unexpected_handler</tt> function. [ <i>Note:</i> A default <tt>unexpected_handler</tt>
is always considered a callable handler in this context. <i>- end note</i> ] 
</p></blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
