<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2112" status="Open">
<title>User-defined classes that cannot be derived from</title>
<section><sref ref="[conforming]"/>,<sref ref="[allocator.traits]"/>,<sref ref="[allocator.adaptor.syn]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>30 Nov 2011</date>
<priority>1</priority>

<discussion>

<p>
It is a very established technique for implementations to derive internally from user-defined class types that are
used to customize some library component, e.g. deleters and allocators are typical candidates. The advantage of this
approach is to possibly take advantage of the empty-base-class optimization (EBCO).
<p/>
Whether or whether not libraries did take advantage of such a detail didn't much matter in C++03. Even though there
did exist a portable idiom to prevent that a class type could be derived from, this idiom has never reached great
popularity: The <a href="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/More_C%2B%2B_Idioms/Final_Class">technique</a> required
to introduce a virtual base class and it did not really prevent the derivation, but only any construction of
such a type. Further, such types are not <em>empty</em> as defined by the <tt>std::is_empty</tt> trait, so
could easily be detected by implementations from TR1 on.
<p/>
With the new C++11 feature of final classes and final member functions it is now very easy to define an empty,
but not derivable from class type. From the point of the user it is quite natural to use this feature for
types that he or she did not foresee to be derivable from.
<p/>
On the other hand, most library implementations (including third-party libraries) often take advantage of EBCO 
applied to user-defined types used to instantiate library templates internally. As the time of submitting this 
issue the following program failed to compile on all tested library implementations:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;memory&gt;

struct Noop <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bold">final</span> {
 template&lt;class Ptr&gt;
 void operator()(Ptr) const {}
};

std::unique_ptr&lt;int, Noop&gt; up;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
In addition, many <tt>std::tuple</tt> implementations with empty, final classes as element types failed as well, 
due to a popular inheritance-based implementation technique. EBCO has also a long tradition to be 
used in library containers to efficiently store potentially stateless, empty allocators.
<p/>
It seems that both user and library did the best they could: None of the affected types did impose explicit
requirements on the corresponding user-defined types to be derivable from (This capability was not part of
the required operations), and libraries did apply EBCO whereever possible to the convenience of the customer.
<p/>
Nonetheless given the existence of non-derivable-from class types in C++11, libraries have to cope with
failing derivations. How should that problem be solved?
<p/>
It would certainly be possible to add weazel wording to the allocator requirements similar to what we had
in C++03, but restricted to derivation-from requirements. I consider this as the bad solution, because it
would add new requirements that never had existed before in this explicit form onto types like allocators.
<p/>
Existing libraries presumably will need internal traits like <tt>__is_final</tt> or <tt>__is_derivable</tt>
to make EBCO possible in the current form but excluding non-derivable class types. As of this writing this
seems to happen already. Problem is that without a <tt>std::is_derivable</tt> trait, third-party libraries
have no portable means to do the same thing as standard library implementations. This should be a good 
reason to make such a trait public available soon, but seems not essential to have now. Further, this issue
should also be considered as a chance to recognice that EBCO has always been a very special corner case
(There exist parallels to the previously existing odd core language rule that did make the interplay 
between <tt>std::auto_ptr</tt> and <tt>std::auto_ptr_ref</tt> possible) and that it would be better to
provide explicit means for space-efficient storage, not necessarily restricted to inheritance relations, 
e.g. by marking data members with a special attribute.
<p/>
At least two descriptions in the current standard should be fixed now for better clarification:
</p>
<ol>
<li><p>As mentioned by Ganesh, <sref ref="[allocator.traits]"/> p1 currently contains a (non-normative) note
"Thus, it is always possible to create a derived class from an allocator." which should be removed.
</p>
</li>
<li><p>As pointed out by Howard, the specification of <tt>scoped_allocator_adaptor</tt> as of
<sref ref="[allocator.adaptor.syn]"/> already requires derivation from <tt>OuterAlloc</tt>, but 
only implies indirectly the same for the inner allocators due to the <em>exposition-only</em> 
description of member <tt>inner</tt>. This indirect implication should be normatively required for 
all participating allocators.
</p></li>
</ol>


<note>2012, Kona</note>
<p>
What we really need is a type trait to indicate if a type can be derived from.  Howard reports
Clang and libc++ have had success with this approach.
</p>
<p>
Howard to provide wording, and AJM to alert Core that we may be wanting to add a new trait
that requires compiler support.
</p>

<note>2014-02, Issaquah: Howard and Daniel comment and provide wording</note>

<p>
Several existing C++11 compilers do already provide an internal <tt>__is_final</tt> intrinsic (e.g. clang and gcc) and therefore 
we believe that this is evidence enough that this feature is implementable today.
<p/>
We believe that both a simple and clear definition of the <tt>is_final</tt> query should result in a true outcome 
if and only if the current existing language definition holds that a complete class type (either union or non-union) 
has been marked with the <i>class-virt-specifier</i> <code>final</code> &mdash; nothing more.
<p/>
The following guidelines lead to the design decision and the wording choice given below:
<p/>
It has been expressed several times that a high-level trait such is "<tt>is_derivable</tt>" would be preferred and
would be more useful for non-experts. One problem with that request is that it is astonishingly hard to find a common denominator 
for what the <em>precise</em> definition of this trait should be, especially regarding corner-cases. Another example of getting very 
differing points of view can obtained by asking a bunch of C++ experts what the best definition of the <tt>is_empty</tt> trait
should be (which can be considered as a kind of higher-level trait).
<p/>
Once we have a fundamental trait like <tt>is_final</tt> available, we can easily define higher-level traits in the future
on top of this by a proper logical combination of the low-level traits.
<p/>
A critical question is whether providing such a low-level compile-time introspection might be considered as a disadvantageous,
because it could constrain the freedom of existing implementations even further and whether a high-level trait would solve
this dilemma. We assert that since C++11 the static introspection capabilities are already very large and we believe that
making the presence or absence of the <tt>final</tt> keyword testable does not make the current situation worse.
<p/>
Below code example demonstrate the intention and the implementability of this feature:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;type_traits&gt;

namespace std
{

template &lt;class T&gt;
struct is_final
  : public integral_constant&lt;bool, __is_final(T)&gt;
{};

}  // std

// test it

union FinalUnion <span style="color:#009900;font-weight:bolder">final</span> { };

union NonFinalUnion { };

class FinalClass <span style="color:#009900;font-weight:bolder">final</span> { };

union NonFinalClass { };

class Incomplete;

int main()
{
  using std::is_final;
  static_assert( is_final&lt;const volatile FinalUnion&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;FinalUnion[]&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;FinalUnion[1]&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;NonFinalUnion>{}, "");
  static_assert( is_final&lt;FinalClass&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;FinalClass&amp;&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;FinalClass*&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;NonFinalClass&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;void&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;int&gt;{}, "");
  static_assert(!is_final&lt;Incomplete&gt;{}, ""); // <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bolder">error incomplete type 'Incomplete' used in type trait expression</span>
}
</pre></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>This wording is relative to N3797.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Change <sref ref="[meta.type.synop]"/>, header <tt>&lt;type_traits&gt;</tt> synopsis, as indicated</p>

<blockquote><pre>
namespace std {
  [&hellip;]
  <i>// 20.10.4.3, type properties:</i>
  [&hellip;]
  template &lt;class T&gt; struct is_empty;
  template &lt;class T&gt; struct is_polymorphic;
  template &lt;class T&gt; struct is_abstract;
  <ins>template &lt;class T&gt; struct is_final;</ins>

  [&hellip;]
}
</pre></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Change <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/>, Table 49 &mdash; Type property predicates, as indicated</p>

<table border="1">
<caption>Table 49 &mdash; Type property predicates</caption>
<tr>
<th>Template</th>
<th>Condition</th>
<th>Preconditions</th>
</tr> 
<tr>
<td>
<tt>template &lt;class T&gt;</tt><br/>
<tt>struct is_abstract;</tt>
</td>
<td>
[&hellip;]
</td>
<td>
[&hellip;]
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<ins><tt>template &lt;class T&gt;</tt><br/>
<tt>struct is_final;</tt></ins>
</td>
<td>
<ins><code>T</code> is a class type marked with the <i>class-virt-specifier</i> <code>final</code> (<sref ref="[class]"/>).<br/> 
[<i>Note:</i> A union is a class type that can be marked with <code>final</code>. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]</ins>
</td>
<td>
<ins>If <tt>T</tt> is a class type, <tt>T</tt> shall be a complete type</ins>
</td>
</tr>

</table>

</li>

<li><p>After <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/> p5 add one further example as indicated:</p>

<blockquote><p>
<ins>[<i>Example</i>:</ins>
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
<ins><i>// Given:</i>
class S { };
struct P final { };
union U1 { };
union U2 final { };

<i>// the following assertions hold:</i>
static_assert(!is_final&lt;int&gt;::value, "Error!");
static_assert(!is_final&lt;void&gt;::value, "Error!");
static_assert(!is_final&lt;S&gt;::value, "Error!");
static_assert( is_final&lt;P&gt;::value, "Error!");
static_assert(!is_final&lt;U1&gt;::value, "Error!");
static_assert( is_final&lt;U2&gt;::value, "Error!");</ins>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
<ins>&mdash; <i>end example</i>]</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
